all right happy Monday everyone today
we're talking about coin swaps massively
improving Bitcoin privacy and
fungibility a lot of excitement around
going swaps so hopefully we can you know
touching some interesting things so yeah
this is a 2020 ongoing github repo paper
that Chris Belanger has been working on
and you can view the original file here
at this link and yeah it's heavily based
on the 2013 work by Greg Maxwell just a
reminder of what we've been doing
wasabi research Club is a weekly meetup
that tries to focus on interesting
philosophical papers math papers privacy
papers around Bitcoin so we cover
different topics and you can see here
we've covered a lot of different topics
in the last a few months we went on a
little bit of hiatus because I was
mostly the one sort of organizing these
things and became a lot less formal in
April and May with casual conversations
and most recently were very excited to
say that wabi-sabi which was sort of the
outcome of all of this discussion and
work we have this new new protocol draft
that's been you know just finished by a
lot of people that are on this call and
and that's very exciting and so now
we're kind of getting back into the into
the swing of things with regular
discussions of paper papers last week we
talked about coin swaps as just a broad
idea like philosophically like what our
coin swaps why we want them how are some
ways we could use coin swaps etc today
we're looking at a specific protocol
going swaps which is Chris Belcher's
2020 paper excellent find out everything
about what we're doing on our github
it's very likely we'll continue to talk
about coins laps in next Monday's
presentation so if you're enjoying coin
swaps then you'll be pretty excited
okay so like any good privacy paper the
coin flops paper begins with a bit of
prose Belcher writes imagine a future
where a user Alice has bitcoins and
wants to send them with maximal privacy
so she creates a special kind of
transaction for anyone looking at the
blockchain her transaction appears
completely normal with their coins
seemingly going from address a to
address B but in reality her coins end
up in address Z which is entirely
unconnected to either A or B and so here
the big thing that Belcher is trying to
talk about when he's bringing up his
coin swaps for protocol is is a concept
of covert miss right and so what is
covert miss we talked about this last
week
covert miss we say that a protocol is
covert if a passive bystander is not
able to differentiate a user of the
protocol with a regular everyday user
who is not engaged in that protocol so
for Bitcoin this means not revealing any
sort of smart contract behavior in the
address format or the transaction format
now if we care about is Cove earnest we
have to admit that that coin joints are
not covert what do we mean by that well
when we look at a coin join yes we can
say you know individuals participating
in a coin join are anonymous
between themselves and there's certain
sort of probabilistic uncertainty in
terms of which blind get output belongs
to which participant but there's no
question to the passive observer that
what's going on before them is a coin
joint it is these these three
individuals are engaged in some sort of
privacy enhancing technique and so in
that way a zero length coin joint is not
covert right when we know people who use
conjure and will who don't use coin
joint and they're very distinct so why
is covert nerves so critical this is
brought up immediately in the paper
Belcher makes a good point he says it
imagine
different user Carroll who doesn't care
at all about privacy and she says her
Bitcoin using a regular wallet which
exists today that isn't conservative
carbon C at all
but because Carole's transaction looks
exactly like Alice's and Alice does care
about privacy alice is doing these
covert coin swaps Carol's transaction is
now possibly Alice's transaction it you
can't be certain but Carol herself is
not engaged in some privacy protocol
because it looks just like Alice
so Carol's privacy is improved even
though she didn't change her behavior
and perhaps had never even heard of the
sovereign so she doesn't care at all
about coin swaps because Alice is
engaged in these covert privacy
protocols she's actually shielding Carol
as well this is a pretty huge property
and coin joint in a sense does offer
this property in a very small amount
because if coin joint participants are
engaged with average everyday users
those average everyday users are getting
a very very office gated coins and so
when they then give those obviously the
Quinns to other users opposite coins
become sort of everywhere but here this
is quite a bit further I think so what
do we mean by covert nests in the conv
and you know in light of coin swaps we
mean that if you have an alice in orange
and Bob in yellow that what they're
doing when they're doing court off
between each other is they're sending
their addresses to a special address
that looks like your average you know
plain pay to public key hash address or
pay to weddings public key hash address
and then from that address they are
switching ownership for from one to the
other and the critical thing here is
that on the blockchain these two graphs
of you know Alice's coin going to this
Brown address and then to yellow address
is completely unconnected that there's
no merging of the graphs from these two
sides so they're completely separate
graphs and so no one knows that this is
happening and so the end result is that
whatever
Bob's history is now Alice's Alice is
inheriting it so bob is a is a British
individual who likes to buy you know
shoes online his history is now going
over to Alice who is then going to
behave totally differently and any
forensics company that's trying to
cluster those behaviors and it's trying
to say you know this graph looks clearly
like Bob well we'll then they met with a
completely different user behavior
because actually it's Alice so this is
totally covert that's what's going on
here so here is Belcher talking about
coin swaps in the very beginning you
could see he outlines it very clearly
here on the bottom the same sort of
chart that I've you know that was on
previous slide and the critical thing to
understand of course is that coin swaps
are non-custodial which means that you
know an alice is not giving her coin up
to Bob hoping that Bob doesn't steal
that coin you know they're using hash
time law contracts and the like to
guarantee that as soon as Bob claims
Alice's coin Alice is now able to claim
Bob's coin this is not very different
from the Lightning Network that we see
and again like I said before this is
heavily based on the 2013 Pro buggering
Maxwell although back then Maxwell had
to use many more transactions and they
were they weren't covert at all it was
quite evident at least that something
fishy was going on that this transaction
was different than an average
transaction and this is not the case
with with with Belcher's work so how is
Belcher making it covert I mean if
Maxwell couldn't make it go ger and how
is Belcher doing that well he's using a
clever trick called ECDSA 2p this is to
party elliptic curve do signature
algorithm so what essentially what it is
is a two of two multi signature address
but it looks the same as a regular
single signature address and any address
can be can be tricked can be converted
into a two-party elliptic curve a
two-party ECDSA so you can use it with
pain and public key hash you can use it
with pen script hash wrapped pain to
witness public key hash or you can use
it with the new back 32 paid a witness
public key hash and there's a big point
that vulture makes here which is which
shows a lot of where he comes from
because I haven't said a lot about about
Chris Beltre because everyone in this
chat knows something about him he is the
privacy wiki maintainer he is the
electro personal server maintainer he is
the joint market maintainer so he's
probably one of the top three people in
the space working on privacy and you can
see that something very smart and what
he says here he says you know all those
more signatures with music provide a
much easier way to and create invisible
to of two multi-state it is not as
suitable for point swap it you might ask
why would a more secure you know a
simpler protocol that's you know that
that that all of the all the new hive is
is talking about why isn't that the way
that Belcher wants to go and the answer
is simple because not enough people are
using this address and what vult really
wants is he wants users who are here's a
coin swap to look like an overwhelming
majority of average people on the
network so he wants people to look like
just everyday old school paid a public
key hash or the newer beta script hash
wrapped and paid into public key hash he
doesn't want to use a new format that is
a very small number of people and so the
property of covert race that's really
important here is it is the one that
I've sort of highlighted here in green
it's the special address that's right
these special addresses we need a to of
to multi stake but we don't want to
reveal that it's a to of two multi-sig
because two of two multi six comprised
of a super minority
both Bitcoin amounts and Bitcoin
addresses on the network so what I would
like to do is we would like to look like
any any wallet blockchain comm wall we
want to look like you know what Saudi
oil that we want to look like mycelium
wall I want to look like we know me well
I want to look at every other common
wall and none of those wallets are
offering to of to multi-sig because
that's quite rare so so so so he saw
this with with a two-party ECDSA the
second thing we have to ask is well how
are we going to avoid a mount
correlation because the the problem you
have is that if an adversary starts
tracking an address of Alice at Point a
they could unmix the points off easily
by searching the entire blockchain for
other transactions of the mouths close
to the amount that alice is using if
it's 15 Bitcoin and you know that
forensics company is simply going to
watch for other addresses that are doing
transactions with exactly 15 Bitcoin
which would lead them to to address
Alice B we can beat this by a not
correlation attack by creating multi
transaction coin swaps what does that
look like well looks like this instead
of Alice you know at the top alice is
gonna swap with Bob so she's gonna have
her 30 bitcoins she's going to swap it
over to Bob who's gonna receive the 30
bitcoins but Bob isn't gonna give Alice
a single utx so instead of bubbling to
give Alice a cluster of utx shows the
amount of 30 bitcoins as you can see
here that now we're introducing not a
single coin swap but but but a triple
point swap Multi multi coin coin swap
here and the net result is that it's
much much harder for anyone on the
outside to find you know those those new
T excels that amount to 30 especially if
Alice herself doesn't have a single UT
Excel but with several new teak shows
that she's exchanging for other UTX
shows as it turns out with this protocol
there are no limitations with both
merging UT exo's in a coin swap but also
branching youtube so isn't a coin swap
so you really don't know if alice is
getting one he takes no to t expose or
12 UT exo's so that's how Belcher
proposes that we prevent
a mountain correlation now let's talk
about trust lessness okay so we're
talking about covert next let's talk
about restlessness a protocol is trust
less if it neither jeopardizes the
security nor the privacy of the users
Bitcoin and their Bitcoin history to any
single party now the coins we've talked
about in the past pretty particular zero
link coin joints are trustless
specifically zero link Chalian blind
coins are trustless because the users do
not give the central coordinator any
additional information about their
addresses now there are other protocols
that don't do these this blinding and
that of course is not trustless but with
with the zero line coin when they are
trustless and of course zero link point
joints rely on the users having to sign
the transactions so if the user believes
they're being screwed over and do not
get that amount of Bitcoin they deserve
back they simply don't sign and there's
no risk to the user of losing bitcoins
but coin swaps are not trustless by
default it's not the security of the of
the Bitcoin that's of concern
it's the privacy of the Bitcoin and why
is that well it should be quite evident
whenever you do a coin swap you are
engaging with one other individual and
so how do you know that one other
individual isn't chained alysus or some
forensics company and how do you know
that individual isn't going to comply or
or collude with a bad actor so clearly
you don't know if the person you're
you're collaborating with is going to
rat you out because they know your
history of coins so how does some
Belcher do this problem while he
introduces this idea of routing coin
swaps now this this diagram here isn't
very accurate there's a more accurate
diagram in a second but the idea is sort
of there so here what you can imagine is
three participants are doing coin swaps
between each other first alice is doing
it with Bob and then out and then with
Bob's coin alice is doing it with Carol
and then finally with Carol's coin she
receives that back and so the idea here
is that coins are bouncing around from
multiple participants such that yes
one participant can know a particular
link but in order for alice's coin to be
anonymized
all of the participants in this coin
swap must Khalid together to D anonymize
her and if this is starting to sound
very similar it's because this sounds
almost exactly like lightning or tor the
fact that we're Onion Routing we're
essentially doing this multiple times
with multiple participants so that
everybody is just one link to the final
destination this is actually very secure
here's a better diagram so you can
imagine that on the left is Alice's coin
and she's switching it for the brown
coin and now she has that brown quench
switching it for a blue coin and then
she has a blue question switch there for
a green coin and then she finally
switches it for one last point and that
is the coin she's deciding to spend from
now on and the important thing is that
all of these links need to be broken in
order for her crimes to be broken and so
Brown blue and green must collude
together to break her privacy so if
Alice wants to avoid dressing Bob Carol
or dead she can trust none of them by
essentially trusting a little all of
them and as long as all of them don't
collude in a conjunction format that is
they all look together
she's pretty much okay so then we have
to combine these two concepts together
so in in the paper Belcher has this
drawing here where Alice has her
multiple coins she switches swapping
them with bombs multiple coins and then
she has Bob's local coins and she's
swapping with Charlie and then she has
Charlie's court she's helped me with
dentists and so forth until she's ready
to spend those coins and the graph is
completely broken and alice has not
trusted Bob or Charlie or Dennis and the
amount correlation is very hard to
perform
here's a slightly better diagram I think
than the one that Belcher gave just
because he was sort of constrained you
know again you just have these these
coin swaps for different coins of the
same total amounts and these coins have
continued sort
indefinitely now Belcher does make a
point that most people will trust one
swab and I think that's kind of an
interesting point that he makes that
most users will trust one or two swabs
and won't need to do many many swaps I
don't know if it's a particularly sound
thing to to suggest because it does
present problems with them with
motivated actors performing a simple
attack although he addresses that later
on so here's another diagram he also
talks about what happens if Alice is a
single UTF so of 15 Bitcoin well Alice
will need to do a branching coin swap
where she doesn't swap for a single coin
rather she swaps for a sixth of Bob's
coins and then those points are then
swapped for Charlie's point and ends
coins and they actually are swapped at
different times with different
participants so not all fifteen coins or
going in the same going in the same path
are actually branching out to different
individuals altogether so makes timing
and I'm not correlation very very hard
and so and Alice ends with a bunch of
coins from Johanna and from Fred and
then if Alice has two large coins and
she needs to consolidate them but she
doesn't want the the histories of those
two points to be merged she can again do
the same thing by switching them from
Bob when Charlie's coins and then
finally merging those points together
because Bob and Charlie's histories are
less critical than analysis history so
something interesting here so so now
Belcher's talking about breaking change
output and wala fingerprinting
heuristics the the first thing we talk
about is is the breaking the change
output so equal output coin joins easily
leak change addresses unless there are
suites with no change right so we know
that that any equal output coin join has
this problem where there is some change
and that changes is what we call own
toxic so this isn't a problem for coin
swap
any big one that you have you can find a
maker an individual who has bitcoins
who's willing to match your amount in
exchange for some some fee so quarrel
doesn't have that that change output
heuristic and this brings up to the next
point which is the walleye
fingerprinting heuristic and here I've
put in bracket the concept of randomness
so I'm just gonna say a little bit of a
personal story which hopefully I can put
up on them on hopefully I can put this
on
Belcher's of privacy wiki but BTC paste
server has a interesting transaction
output ordering for inputs so when when
when a be steep a server when you use
the B TCP server wallet and you send
money from within the BTC pay server
what it will do is it will sort of
randomly organize the inputs so
typically when you look at you know
businesses that get a lot of inputs you
get a lot of coins into their business
when they want to spend typically
businesses will either order my amount
whether it's reverse ordering or you
know high to low and low to high or they
will order by time that the Bitcoin has
a trident wallet
what be cheap a server didn't do that
they decided to do it randomly so they
took all their inputs and they and you
know it's random it's not my timings not
my amount now you might think wow this
is brilliant you know we'll use
randomness and and now we see pay server
doesn't you know you know add some
privacy to the merchants that use that
service unfortunately that's not the
case it's the opposite reality because
very few people use randomness and so
the result is that randomness is a
fingerprint so you know Belcher pointed
this out and it's a very good point he
he brings up here he says we can break
this heuristic by having makers randomly
with some probability send their change
to an address they've used before he's
talking here about a different heuristic
about the heuristic of
[Music]
the address is being reused or likely
payment addresses you know for example I
want to pay you money and I'm likely to
reuse your address but change addresses
are always brand new he's saying well
why don't we just have a small
probability of changed dresses being
reused on purpose and again some people
might say well don't should we never
reuse the dress
well actually what you're saying is it's
totally correct we should be behaving
like the crowd so that forensics
companies can't say anything
probabilistically artistically about our
particular protocol and actually it was
how we did a very similar thing I think
was how we did this about RBF recently
like we're a few months ago where we
found out that you know if there's like
something like 7% of BEC 32 spends I
have RBF enabled so we just we just made
it so that was Tommy wallets have like
seven percent of the time wasabi
transactions have RBF so it's
purposefully it's not random it's it's
looking similar to what other people are
doing so another great here is to kiki
attacks in the script type heuristic he
says why don't we just purposefully make
the address address wrong I would use
just look like the address format of the
rest of the network and this is also a
quite clever although there's some
downside I'm not using the most
efficient address format because that
results in higher fees so there was a
lot of other other things to talk about
in in this paper and I think it pretty
it likely merits in part two series
I was hoping Belcher's here at all he's
currently hearing that Chris no okay so
I was hoping to have it to have him on
here and answer some questions so far
but why don't we leave it there for now
and yeah questions comments
about what but what do you think that
should be the only because based on that
you know conjunction often stops and
burns Antony much more what should be
the end goal of different privacy the
end user experience can you describe it
so I can describe you what I user
experience of conjoined could be which
is actually to which is very small
dramatic enjoins too often conjoins and
that would result in every transaction
being a con Johnny so so that that's one
the TP as instant as it can be however
there is another one large engines for
there's a lot of privacy but if you take
like a total of Patrick after 20 or 40
organelle and for you to to be open open
your wallet and and then you can spawn
the occurrence so so what what how would
it look like
we need coins for tonight well it maxes
on the line and I'm sure he can jump in
and start to say where his end goal is
max
seven running them here other than us
okay well yeah it's a good question I
think the problem with coin swaps alone
is you still the way I see the privacy
and anonymity networks is you're trying
to smell user behavior and figure out
where users are and so I don't see like
one solution fits all where everything
is just solved
now you still have privacy problems you
know for example like let's say you're
just a merchant and you know you're
getting all these payments from people
that are doing these coin swaps so yeah
like that graph is really obfuscated but
now you have all these payments what do
you do I think for a lot of large
business cases and large users
I think coin join still is the most
effective because it just it just
crushes the the gravity it makes the
graph incredibly hard to to unravel yeah
makes sense
now I actually really like to hear
someone else talk as well just because
I'm not familiar with the different
wallets fingerprints what kind of things
left believes these I mean yeah I can
talk about that in depth I actually I
fingerprint a lot of bullets so so yeah
I actually can look at the blockchain
with pretty good accuracy and figure out
which which user is using which wallet I
mean it's everything right so so you
know you know when when I say a
transaction in the blockchain
what kind of address format okay that's
an easy one what kind of is the change
of dress a bit 69 is it indexed
lexicographically or is it just randomly
indexed okay that gives something away
what's the long time is it 0 or is it a
recent block what's the end sequence you
know what's the version number of that
transaction on the change address where
you used like block ENCOM okay that's
easy one you know that you know it's the
case sometimes I noticed that a wallet
will pay to like type outputs okay bingo
only a couple of wallets offer that
advanced feature so I immediately know
no it's what's going on on you know all
of these things like it's it becomes
quickly it becomes oh here's a good one
the transaction fee what kind of a
number is it is it a whole number or is
it a partial number is it when I look at
the blockchain at that time is it is it
based on electrons on a fee distribution
or big link or speed distribution is it
based on you know does the user get to
manually pick or are the three based
options you know these are things that
are pretty quickly revealed there are
probably like twenty to thirty qualities
of a transaction and the problem with
having a lot of qualities is that if you
repeat qualities you become a snowflake
which means you become
unique right no other wall is gonna have
the same twenty qualities that you do
and so for that reason someone like me I
have a pretty easy time like like
deciphering you know transactions
literally to which wallet was based on
nothing but but but one transaction all
right interesting okay yeah - for clear
and end out
and also the transaction backdraft the
deafhood well each if everything else
fails and that means the final clue of
what happened here